<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Usability Study on Ura Design</title>
    <link>http://test.ura.design/tags/usability-study/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Usability Study on Ura Design</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Some rights reserved. Unless otherwise noted, content on this page is under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;License&#34;&gt; Creative Commons license&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 12:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://test.ura.design/tags/usability-study/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>SecureDrop Style Guide</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/blog/securedrop-styleguide/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/blog/securedrop-styleguide/</guid>
      <description>Our next project, in the series of funding from OpenTechFund, is SecureDrop. SecureDrop is an open source whistleblower submission system that media organizations can install to securely accept documents from anonymous sources.
During this process we were brought closer with the Project, getting to know the developers and designers behind it that help create a secure system for whistleblowers. The work we conducted with SecureDrop was part of the OTF Usability Lab, as have been previous ones before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I2P Style Guide and Usability Study</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/blog/i2p-usability-study-and-styleguide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/blog/i2p-usability-study-and-styleguide/</guid>
      <description>Back when Ura was founded in 2016 we only had a small landing page and a Patreon to help fund the time we help Open Source projects. It was very little but the thought that people would support us kept us fueled. During that time we were also approached by I2P for helping them with updating their website and some branding. We resided to simplify the logo to something which would offer more flexibility and be already an improvement of the former logo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thunderbird Style Guide and Usability Study</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/blog/thunderbird-style-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 08:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/blog/thunderbird-style-guide/</guid>
      <description>Since early on, we had a special connection with Thunderbird. While many users moved to web-based mail clients, we always preferred using a single mail client to manage our mail and calendar. In fact, in the early days our founder Elio helped redesign the Thunderbird Conversations add-on and even now our email infrastructure is powered by ProtonMail and ProtonMail Bridge via Thunderbird.
Unfortunately, Mozilla moving away from Thunderbird created technical and design debt throughout the past years, resulting in a wider gap between Firefox and Thunderbird.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
