<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Services on Ura Design</title>
    <link>http://test.ura.design/services/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Services on Ura Design</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Some rights reserved. Unless otherwise noted, content on this page is under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; title=&#34;License&#34;&gt; Creative Commons license&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright><atom:link href="http://test.ura.design/services/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Branding</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/branding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/branding/</guid>
      <description>Visual identity can often be an afterthought, especially in open source. We want to change this status quo and work with you to understand the character and story of your identity better. Our branding services range from logo design to layout design as well as print. No matter if you need a small refresh or a complete overhaul, we will work with you all the way to the finish line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessibility</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/accessibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/accessibility/</guid>
      <description>We consider accessibility a requirement and not a bonus. Getting a 100% rating on an automated accessibility checker is not enough. We provide manual and automated accessibility testing, including best practices in design and development to ensure that your project is compliant with ADA, Section 508 using WCAG 2.1 AA or higher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UX Research</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/ux-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/ux-research/</guid>
      <description>From information architecture to usability testing, we provide the right tools and skills you need for a human-centered design approach. We apply our industry experience to your project using Nielsen Norman’s 10 user experience heuristics. We want to help you build the right thing from the start, instead of fixing things afterward. When it comes to user testing we do provide recruitment and testing services in-house, including user interviews and usability testing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interaction Design</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/interaction-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/interaction-design/</guid>
      <description>We design and build privacy-respecting user interfaces and design systems to bring your vision to life. From sketch to high-fidelity prototype, we cover the end-to-end design process of your website, web app, or mobile app including developer handoff, animations, and interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illustrations</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/illustrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/illustrations/</guid>
      <description>Complex solutions require simple explanations. Allow us to help you with custom illustrations fitting your brand and storytelling. We stray away from stock images in order to craft visuals tailored for you, not for others. From concept to implementation our hand-drawn illustrations will breathe life into your app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Development</title>
      <link>http://test.ura.design/services/web-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://test.ura.design/services/web-development/</guid>
      <description>We are not your usual WordPress website developers. While working with dozens of open source communities we understood that no one wants to maintain a backend for a simple website. We specialize in static site generators such as Hugo or Jekyll to craft websites.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
